<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml><records><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Cologna, Viktoria</author><author>Mede, Niels G.</author><author>Berger, Sebastian</author><author>Besley, John</author><author>Brick, Cameron</author><author>Joubert, Marina</author><author>Maibach, Edward</author><author>Mihelj, Sabina</author><author>Oreskes, Naomi</author><author>Schäfer, Mike S.</author><author>Linden, Dr Sander van der</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Trust in scientists and their role in society across 67 countries</title></titles><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-01-25</date></pub-dates></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.31219/osf.io/6ay7s</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Scientific information is crucial for evidence-based decision-making. Public trust in science can help decision-makers act based on the best available evidence, especially during crises such as climate change or the COVID-19 pandemic. However, in recent years the epistemic authority of science has been challenged, causing concerns about low public trust in scientists. Here we interrogated these concerns with a pre-registered 67-country survey of 71,417 respondents on all inhabited continents and find that in most countries, a majority of the public trust scientists and think that scientists should be more engaged in policymaking. We further show that there is a discrepancy between the public’s perceived and desired priorities of scientific research. Moreover, we find variations between and within countries, which we explain with individual- and country-level variables, including political orientation. While these results do not show widespread lack of trust in scientists, we cannot discount the concern that lack of trust in scientists by even a small minority may affect considerations of scientific evidence in policymaking. These findings have implications for scientists and policymakers seeking to maintain and increase trust in scientists.</abstract><remote-database-name>osf.io</remote-database-name><language>en-us</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://osf.io/6ay7s</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>/home/rachel/snap/zotero-snap/common/Zotero/storage/ZC5UYJ3V/Cologna et al. - 2024 - Trust in scientists and their role in society acro.pdf</url></pdf-urls><text-urls><url>/home/rachel/snap/zotero-snap/common/Zotero/storage/3C35PRS9/6ay7s.html</url></text-urls></urls><access-date>2024-03-18 08:54:32</access-date></record></records></xml>